{"tossups": [{"question": "Responses to these documents were penned by Robert Yates, George Clinton, and Mercy Otis Warren. The fifty-first of these documents praises \"the greatest of all reflections of human nature\" in a description of \"checks and balances.\" For 10 points, name these documents which were written by John Jay, James Madison and Alexander Hamilton in favor of the Constitution.", "answer": "<b><u>Federalist Papers</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The third generation of this group was bankrupted in 1981 by a lawsuit engineered by Morris Dees. This group originally formed in Pulaski, Tennessee and was targeted by the Force Act, but formed again after a 1915 meeting on Stone Mountain. Nathan Bedford Forrest was the original Grand Wizard of this group, which targeted Republicans and black voters. For ten points, name this white supremacist organization, which dressed in white hoods.", "answer": "<b><u>Ku Klu Klan</u></b> or <b><u>KKK</u></b> or the <b><u>Klan</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This person's name was formerly used for the capital of Tajikistan, now known as Dushanbe (<b>doo-SHAHN-bay</b>), and for the mountain now called Ismail Samani (<b>suh-MAH-nee</b>) Peak, which was called \"Communism Peak\" after his death. For 10 points, identify this former namesake of Volgograd, where a major World War II battle was fought in the Soviet Union.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>Stalin</u></b> [Iosif Vissarionovich <b><u>Stalin</u></b>; or Ioseb Besarionis Dze <b><u>Jugashvili</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This modern-day country was converted by Saint Frumentius in the 4th century. The rock-cut city of Lalibela is in this country, where inscriptions in the Ge'ez language appear on stone stelae in the ancient city of Axum. The coffee plant was first grown in this modern-day country. For 10 points, name this African country which lost access to the Red Sea when Eritrea seceded.", "answer": "<b><u>Ethiopia</u></b> [or '<b><u>Ityoppya</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "These agreements were condemned by the United Nations in Resolution 33/28 A. As a result of signing these agreements, one negotiator was killed by Khalid Islambouli and Islamic Jihad. These agreements established the border and a peace agreement between Egypt and Israel. For 10 points, name these 1978 agreements negotiated by Jimmy Carter at a Presidential retreat.", "answer": "<b><u>Camp David</u></b> Accords", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was drafted in the 21st round by the Philadelphia Eagles in 1958, but a knee injury ended his playing career a year later. However, during the 1970's, he led the Oakland Raiders to a 76.3% winning percentage in the 142 regular season games he coached. He later was as a commentator for ABC's Monday Night Football. For 10 points, name this former football player, coach, and commentator who is known for endorsing NFL-based video games bearing his name.", "answer": "John <b><u>Madden</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man, who had a vision of dew falling on grass during a solar eclipse, was interviewed by Thomas Gray after his capture. This man killed the Travis family before his capture at Jerusalem, and he is fictionalized in a William Styron book about his \"confessions.\" For 10 points, name this leader of an 1831 slave rebellion in southeastern Virginia.", "answer": "Nat <b><u>Turner</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Many participants in this event came from Mary Ann M'Clintock's Yearly Meeting movement, which sought to reform decision-making among Quakers. Frederick Douglass spoke at this event, which adopted the Declaration of Sentiments. For 10 points, name this 1848 convention at which Lucretia Mott and Elizabeth Cady Stanton began the women's rights movement.", "answer": "<b><u>Seneca Falls</u></b> Convention", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This instrument's Pleyel models were preferred by its greatest twentieth-century player, Wanda Landowska. The \"art\" of playing this instrument was discussed by Fran\u00e7ois Couperin, and Domenico Scarlatti wrote extensively for it. For 10 points, name this instrument for which J.S. Bach frequently composed, which plucks strings instead of striking them like the later piano.", "answer": "<b><u>harpsichord</u></b> <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 1 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The Tokyo Two were members of this group arrested for stealing cetacean meat. This organization was funded by an Irving-Stowe-arranged benefit concert at Amchitka. A ship belonging to it was docked at a New Zealand harbor when it was bombed by French agents; that ship was the Rainbow Warrior. For 10 points, name this militant environmentalist group", "answer": "<b><u>Greenpeace</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Oscar Kokoschka depicted Alma Mahler as this kind of person \u201cof the Wind.\u201d A Rembrandt depiction of this kind of person was thought to be a father giving his daughter a necklace. Another kind of person is shown wearing a green dress and having a dog at her feet. For 10 points, name this type of person who in a Jan van Eyck (<b>Yon van IKE</b>) portrait marries Giovanni Arnolfini.", "answer": "<b><u>Bride</u></b> [or equivalents, such as <b><u>female spouses</u></b> or <b><u>female marriage partners</u></b>; or specific answers, such as <em>The</em> <em><b><u>Jewish Bride</u></b></em>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "A founder of one of these parties in Italy argued states maintain power through controlling culture in his <em>Prison Notebooks</em>. Parties by this name were instructed to join Popular Fronts during the 1930s to oppose fascism. This party is still the dominant political party in Laos and Vietnam. For 10 points, name these parties promoting the theories of Karl Marx.", "answer": "<b><u>Communist</u></b> parties", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This empire built the Qhapaq \u00d1an by pioneering a forced labor system called <em>mit'a</em>. Messengers called chasquis relayed messages along its elaborate road system, which was paved with stone so llamas and alpacas could traverse them. For 10 points, name this South American empire run from Cuzco, which built Machu Picchu.", "answer": "<b><u>Inca</u></b>n Empire [accept <b><u>Tawantinsuyu</u></b> before mention]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, French forces mutinied en masse following the failure of the Nivelle Offensive. Alexander Samsonov was killed during it when un-coded radio messages helped lead to the defeat of two Russian armies at Tannenberg. Anzac Day celebrates the Australians and New Zealanders who died during this war. For 10 points, name this 1914 to 1918 war.", "answer": "<b><u>World War I</u></b> [or the <b><u>Great War</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man and his wife made the first English translation of Agricola's Latin text on mining, <em>De</em> <em>Rerum Metallica</em>. He often conversed with his wife in Mandarin, and was the leader of Belgian food relief efforts after World War I. For 10 points, name this President who defeated Al Smith for election but suffered the start of the Great Depression in his first year in office.", "answer": "Herbert <b><u>Hoover</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This author was to be profiled by C.S. Forester after his career as a fighter pilot ended, but chose to begin his own writing career instead with an autobiographical article. He also wrote the memoir <em>Going Solo</em>, and this man\u2019s Norwegian mother named him after the first man to reach the South Pole. For 10 points, name this author of <em>James and the Giant Peach</em> and <em>Charlie and</em> <em>the Chocolate Factory.</em>", "answer": "<em></em> Roald <b><u>Dahl</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "An advocate of this philosophy wrote <em>The Great Divorce</em> and the early feminist text <em>Woman in</em> <em>the Nineteenth Century</em>. This philosophy, whose journal <em>The Dial</em> was edited by Margaret Fuller, also included the man who wrote \"that government is best which governs least.\" For 10 points, name this philosophy of mid-nineteenth-century Americans such as Henry David Thoreau.", "answer": "<b><u>transcendental</u></b>ism", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>An anonymous proposal suggested finding this value by having wounded dogs bark at</u></b> <b><u>regular intervals. After the Scilly Islands disaster in 1707, a prize was created for the</u></b> <b><u>person who could create a (+)</u> method for finding this value. Some of that prize money was awarded to John Harrison, whose marine (*)</b> chronometer gave sailors an accurate time that could be used to calculate it. For 10 points, name this geographic coordinate that identifies East-West position, as opposed to latitude.", "answer": "<b><u>longitude</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Saint Telemachus was stoned to death while attempting to stop an event involving these</u></b> <b><u>people. These people, who were managed by a</u> </b><em><b><u>lanista</u></b></em><b><u>, participated in the most famous of</u></b> <b><u>the</u> </b><em><b><u>munera</u></b></em><b><u>. One of these people led a 73 BC (+)</u> revolt that was put down by Crassus. Types of these people include the </b><em><b>murmillones</b></em><b>, who had fish-shaped crests on their (*) </b>helmets, and the <em>retiarii</em>, who used nets. For 10 points, name these Romans, including Spartacus, who engaged in public armed combat for entertainment.", "answer": "<b><u>gladiator</u></b>s [or <b><u>gladiatore</u></b>s; prompt on \u201cRoman <b><u>slave</u></b>s\u201d]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This modern-day country was the birthplace of an order founded by Stephen Hunting</u></b> <b><u>and spread by St. Bernard, the Cistercians. During a massacre of heretics in this country,</u></b> <b><u>the order \"kill them (+)</u> all- God will know his own\" was given. After the death of Peter of Castelnau in this country, Innocent III ordered a campaign against the gnostic (*)</b> Cathars of this country, the Albigensian crusade. For 10 points, name this country, home to the Cluny Abbey in its Aquitaine region.", "answer": "<b><u>France</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man attempted to use Gamma Draconis to measure the distance to a star using</u></b> <b><u>parallax, but was unable to obtain accurate measurements. This man's observations of a</u></b> <b><u>cork plant are collected in his (+)</u></b> <em><b>Micrographia</b></em><b>. This longtime leader of the Royal Society in the late seventeenth century also proposed a (*)</b> \"restoring force\" proportional to distance. For 10 points, name this English polymath who lends his name to a law for the action of springs.", "answer": "Robert <b><u>Hooke</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "<b><u>A popular hippie song said to \"wear a flower in your hair\" when travelling to this city.</u></b> <b><u>This city suffered the \"White Night (+)</u> riots\" following the acquittal of a former supervisor who used the \"twinkie defense\" after killing George Moscone and (*)</b> Harvey Milk. In 1989, this city was hit by an earthquake while hosting a World Series game. For 10 points, name this city where historic districts such as The Mission and Haight-Ashbury are located.", "answer": "<b><u>San Francisco</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This character was created in 1941 for</u> </b><em><b><u>Pep Comics</u></b></em><b><u>. He is the namesake of a company</u></b> <b><u>that published</u> </b><em><b><u>Super Cops</u> </b></em><b><u>and</u> </b><em><b><u>Mighty Crusaders</u></b></em><b><u> under the Red Circle imprint, and he</u></b> <b><u>often irritates the wealthy Mr. (+)</u> Lodge. In the 1970s, this character was the leader of a fictional band that sang the song (*)</b> \"Sugar, Sugar.\" For 10 points, name this red-haired comic book character who hangs out in Riverdale with Jughead, Betty and Veronica.", "answer": "<b><u>Archie</u></b> Andrews", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>Protestors in this country in 2014 often wore the number forty-three painted on their</u></b> <b><u>faces, a reminder of the September 2014 abduction of forty-three (+)</u> students at a teachers' college here. Protests targeted this country's president, who represents the (*)</b> PRI and defeated the incumbent PAN in the 2012 election. For 10 points, name this country where protestors demanded the resignation of Enrique Pe\u00f1a Nieto (en-REE-kay PEN-yah nee-EY-toe).", "answer": "<b><u>Mexico</u></b> [or <b><u>United Mexican States</u></b>; or <b><u>Estados Unidos Mexicanos</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This state\u2019s loss at the first Battle of Himera led to the downfall of its Magonid dynasty.</u></b> <b><u>The Fabian strategy was developed to fight the armies of this city, which won battles at (+)</u></b> <b>Trebia and Lake Trasimene after one of its commanders crossed the (*)</b> Alps. Cato the Elder famously ended his speeches by declaring that this city \u201cmust be destroyed\u201d, or \u201c<em>delenda est</em>\u201d. For 10 points, name this city-state whose armies, led by Hamilcar and Hannibal Barca, fought Rome in the Punic Wars.", "answer": "<b><u>Carthage</u></b> [or <b><u>Carthago</u></b>; or <b><u>Kart-hadasht</u></b>]  <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 1 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras \u2013 ONLY READ IF YOU NEED A BACKUP OR TIEBREAKER! </b> <b><u>This lover of Manuela Saenz authorized the killing of any</u> </b><em><b><u>peninsulares</u></b></em><b><u> who didn't follow</u></b> <b><u>him by issuing the Decree of War to the Death during his Admirable Campaign. Years</u></b> <b><u>after winning the battle of (+)</u> Boyac\u00e1, he traveled west to the Guayaquil conference to plan for the future with Jos\u00e9 de (*)</b> San Martin. In 2010, Hugo Chavez claimed to have exhumed this general's bones. For 10 points, name this \"Liberator\" who fought to free Venezuela and Colombia from Spanish rule.  ANSWER: Sim\u00f3n <b><u>Bol\u00edvar</u></b> [or Sim\u00f3n Jose Antonio de la Santisima Trinidad <b>Bol\u00edvar </b>y Palacios Ponte y Blanco]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}